Guide to the Time Inc. New Media Records: Editor Daniel Okrent Files 1989-2001 MS 3009-RG 45
New-York Historical Society
Time Inc. New Media Records: Editor Daniel Okrent Files
1989-2001
New-York Historical Society
Time, inc.
MS 3009-RG 45
4.5 Linear feet in 5 record cartons
The Time Inc. New Media Records contain Daniel Okrent's files created while he was Editor of New Media and document this department's management of Time Inc.'s internet projects including websites for each magazine.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers with the exception of restricted materials. Restricted materials include personnel records dated after 1975; personnel performance evaluations; contracts and agreements; and records with personally identifiable information. Restricted materials are located in box R38.
Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact manuscripts@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Historical Note
According to records about Time Inc. Multimedia/Time Inc. New Media in the Time Inc. Subject Files (MS 3009-RG 1), Time Inc. created the New Media department in November 1993 in preparation for the testing of an interactive cable TV service with the appointment of Walter Isaacson as editor. At this time, the department Time Inc. Multimedia already existed separately. In 1994, Time magazine announced it was planning "a World Wide Web 'site'" and began testing of Pathfinder in October 1994 with supervision from both Time Inc. Multimedia and New Media. Pathfinder was an early Time Warner website containing editorial material from all Time Warner divisions including Time Inc. magazines. By mid-1997, news articles indicate that Pathfinder was struggling, and Time Inc. abandoned it at some point in favor of maintaining individual websites for each magazine.
When head of Multimedia Curt Viebranz left Time Inc., Isaacson and New Media took over management of Time Inc.'s online, cable online and electronic distribution of content. In January 1995, Paul Sagan was appointed Senior Vice President of New Media, later becoming President and Editor of New Media. In June 1996 New Media appointed Meg Siesfeld as the Managing Editor, responsible for the continuing development of Pathfinder. Sagan resigned at the end of 1996 with Danial Okrent replacing him as Editor of New Media. In February 1997, Time Inc. appointed Craig Forman as the Editor-at-Large for New Media. In April 1997, Linda McCutcheon Conneally was appointed as President of New Media, filling the position left by Sagan. It isn't documented how long after her resignation from Time Inc. in April 1999 the New Media department remained in existence.
Other projects managed by New Media included participation in the launch of Road Runner high speed cable internet in September 1996, a service created by the Excalibur Group, a joint venture of Time Warner Cable and Time Inc.; Thrive, a joint venture between Time Inc. and America Online providing content about healthy living; and Money.com Plus, a subscription personal finance website with partner Thomson Financial Services.
Biographical Note
Daniel Okrent joined Life in 1989 as a consultant and contributing editor before being appointed as the Assistant Managing Editor. In December 1992, he was appointed the Life Managing Editor.
Daniel Okrent joined the New Media department as Editor at the end of 1996, taking over one of the roles vacated by Paul Sagan. According to a November 1996 news release announcing Okrent's appointment, he "will oversee the editorial content of the company's online, cable online and Internet publishing activities. In addition to his responsibilities for Pathfinder... Okrent will work closely with the managing editors of the Time Inc. magazines to fully exploit the online opportunities for each of the company's titles." and "work with ...outside content providers interested in pursuing new media initiatives with Time Inc." Okrent served two years in this position before being named Time Inc. Editor-at-Large in March 1999.
Aside from his work at Time Inc., Okrent was a writer and participated as a commentator in Ken Burns's documentary on baseball.
Citation:
Time Inc. Bio Files, MS 3009-RG 2, New-York Historical Society.
Provenance
Gift of Time Inc. in 2015.
Related Archival Materials Note
This finding aid relates to just one record group of the Time Inc. Records. For information about the other record groups and for overall information about the archives, please see the Guide to the Time Inc. Records (MS 3009). The Henry Luce Papers (MS 3014) were acquired with the Time Inc. Records. The collection of books acquired with the records are cataloged as the Time Inc. Reference Library. Additional records on the New Media department and Daniel Okrent are located in the Time Inc. Subject Files (MS 3009-RG 1) and the Time Inc. Bio Files (MS 3009-RG 2).
Scope and Contents
Daniel Okrent Files include his correspondence and subject files created during his tenure as Editor of New Media and document this department's management of Time Inc.'s internet projects including websites for each magazine. The paperwork transferring Okrent's files to the archives is in his Bio file. Some files from his time as Managing Editor of Life were included in the transfer and remain with these files.
Corporations -- History; Corporations -- New York (State) -- New York.; Corporation records; Internet industry; Mass media -- United States; Online information services industry; Organization files; Publishers and publishing -- New York (State) -- New York.; Time, inc. -- Archives; Time, inc. -- History; Okrent, Daniel, 1948-
- Series I. Correspondence, 1993-2001; 2.25 Linear feet in 3 record cartons
  Scope and Contents
  Okrent's correspondence is a mix of business and personal. Records include interoffice memoranda, correspondence from companies interested in partnerships, invitations to professional events, and some correspondence from users of Time Inc. websites and discussion boards. Personal correspondence includes that related to Okrent's professional work outside of Time Inc. as a writer and commentator.
  His correspondence from 1996 also includes transcripts and other material for John Loengard's Life oral history project and remains with these files in the original order.
  Arrangement
  Organized chronologically. Based on the original order, correspondence maintains two sets of A-Z miscellaneous with some specific titled folders included in alphabetical order. The first set of correspondenced has dates beginning with 1996 and the second set has dates beginning with 1999. Folders that belong to neither group are filed in chronological order.
  - Pearlstine, Norm: Memoranda to and from, 1995-1999 (Offsite-box 3827, Folder 1)
  - Pearlstine, Norm: Staff Changes Memoranda, 1995-1998 (Offsite-box 3827, Folder 2)
  - A Miscellaneous, 1996-1998 (Offsite-box 3827, Folder 3)
  - B Miscellaneous, 1996-1998 (Offsite-box 3827, Folder 4-5)
  - C Miscellaneous, 1996-1998 (Offsite-box 3827, Folder 6)
  - D Miscellaneous, 1996-1998 (Offsite-box 3827, Folder 7)
  - E Miscellaneous, 1996-1998 (Offsite-box 3827, Folder 8)
  - F Miscellaneous, 1996-1998 (Offsite-box 3827, Folder 9-10)
  - G Miscellaneous, 1996-1998 (Offsite-box 3827, Folder 11)
  - H Miscellaneous, 1996-1998 (Offsite-box 3827, Folder 12)
  - I Miscellaneous, 1996-1998 (Offsite-box 3827, Folder 13)
  - J Miscellaneous, 1996-1998 (Offsite-box 3827, Folder 14)
  - K Miscellaneous, 1996-1998 (Offsite-box 3827, Folder 15)
  - L Miscellaneous, 1996-1998 (Offsite-box 3827, Folder 16)
  - M Miscellaneous, 1996-1998 (Offsite-box 3827, Folder 17-18)
  - Mc Miscellaneous, 1996-1998 (Offsite-box 3827, Folder 19)
  - McGwire, Mark, 1998 (Offsite-box 3827, Folder 20)
  - McPartland, Marian, 1998 (Offsite-box 3827, Folder 21)
  - N Miscellaneous, 1996-1998 (Offsite-box 3827, Folder 22)
  - O Miscellaneous, 1996-1998 (Offsite-box 3827, Folder 23)
  - P Miscellaneous, 1996-1998 (Offsite-box 3827, Folder 24)
  - Q Miscellaneous, 1996-1998 (Offsite-box 3827, Folder 25)
  - R Miscellaneous, 1996-1998 (Offsite-box 3827, Folder 26)
  - S Miscellaneous, 1996-1998 (Offsite-box 3827, Folder 27-28)
  - Sinatra and Pop Culture, 1998 (Offsite-box 3827, Folder 29)
  - T Miscellaneous, 1996-1998 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 1)
  - U Miscellaneous, 1996-1998 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 2)
  - V Miscellaneous, 1996-1998 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 3)
  - W Miscellaneous, 1996-1998 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 4)
  - XYZ Miscellaneous, 1996-1998 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1997-1998 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 6)
  - A Miscellaneous, 1999-2000 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 7)
  - B Miscellaneous, 1999-2000 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 8)
  - C Miscellaneous, 1999-2001 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 9)
  - D Miscellaneous, 1999-2001 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 10)
  - E Miscellaneous, 1999 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 11)
  - Editorial Guidelines, 1997 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 12)
  - F Miscellaneous, 1999-2001 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 13)
  - G Miscellaneous, 1999-2001 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 14)
  - H Miscellaneous, 1999 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 15)
  - I Miscellaneous, 1999 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 16)
  - Idea Submission Form Letter, 1997-1999 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 17)
  - J Miscellaneous, 1999 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 18)
  - K Miscellaneous, 1999-2000 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 19)
  - Kiosk Project, 1998 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 20)
  - L Miscellaneous, 1999 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 21)
  - Lamb, David, 2000 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 22)
  - Lycos, 1997 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 23)
  - M Miscellaneous, 1999-2000 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 24)
  - Magazine Ideas, 1997 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 25)
  - Marketing Memoranda, 1997 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 26)
  - MIT Media Lab, 1997 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 27)
  - Mc Miscellaneous, 1999 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 28)
  - McDonald, Scott, 1997 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 29)
  - McKinsey, 1997 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 30)
  - N Miscellaneous, 1999-2000 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 31)
  - Nagourney, David, 1999 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 32)
  - Nylen, Bob/Waldman, Steve: BeliefOnline.com, 1999 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 33-34)
  - O Miscellaneous [empty], 1999 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 35)
  - P Miscellaneous, 1999 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 36)
  - Photographers: Life: John Loengard Interview Project, 1993-1996 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 37-38)
  - Photography, 1996 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 39)
  - Popular Science, 2001 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 40)
  - Principal for a Day, 1996-2000 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 41-46)
  - Privacy, 1998 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 47)
  - Q Miscellaneous [empty], 1999 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 48)
  - R Miscellaneous, 1999-2001 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 49)
  - Ratings, Internet, 1998 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 50)
  - Recreational Software Advisory Committee, 1997 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 51)
  - Rowan, Doug: Interlane Images Entertainment, 1998 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 52)
  - Ryan, Kevin: People Online, 1999 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 53)
  - S Miscellaneous, 1999-2000 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 54)
  - Search Engines Memorandum, 1997 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 55)
  - The Sign, 1996 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 56)
  - Smith, Danyel, 1999 (Offsite-box 3828, Folder 57)
  - Smith, Mike: Customer Summary, 1999 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 1)
  - T Miscellaneous, 1999 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 2)
  - U Miscellaneous [empty], 1999 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 3)
  - V Miscellaneous, 1999 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 4)
  - W Miscellaneous, 1999 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 5)
  - XYZ Miscellaneous, 1999 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 6)
  - Zentmyer, Dave: Lands End, 1998 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 7)
- Series II. Subject Files, 1989-2001; 2.25 Linear feet in 3 record cartons
  The Subject Files are Okrent's office files on various projects and subjects related to his work as Editor of New Media. Items of interest include webpage printouts of Pathfinder; some user commentary on Pathfinder; and a New Media Department strategy workshop organized by McKinsey & Co.
  Organized alphabetically.
  - Advertising, 1997 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 8)
  - Ad File, 1997 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 9)
  - Allpolitics, 1997 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 10)
  - AOL-Time Warner, 2000-2001 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 11)
  - Ask Dr. Weil, 1996-1997 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 12)
  - Ask Dr. Weil [RESTRICTED], 1997 (Offsite-box R38)
  - AskJeeves.com, 1998 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 13)
  - ASME (American Society of Magazine Editors) Guidelines: Advertising, 1989-1999 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 14)
  - ASME (American Society of Magazine Editors) Online, 1996 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 15)
  - Audible Inc., 1999 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 16)
  - Audible Inc. [RESTRICTED], 1999 (Offsite-box R38)
  - Bankable Ideas, 1997 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 17)
  - Box Scores, 1997 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 18)
  - Budget and Forecast, 1996 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 19)
  - Bulletin Boards, 1997 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 20)
  - Calio, Jim: Video Magazines, 1992 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 21)
  - Cannon, Graham, 1997 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 22)
  - Casey, Susan: Sports Illustrated Women, 2001 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 23)
  - Catro, Janice, 1997 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 24)
  - CNN [empty], circa 1997 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 25)
  - Compuserve [RESTRICTED], 1997-1998 (Offsite-box R38)
  - Conflict of Interest, 1998 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 26)
  - Contracts [RESTRICTED], 1997 (Offsite-box R38)
  - Contract Letters (Form), 1999 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 27)
  - Consumer Research, 1996-1997 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 28)
  - Corbis, 1996 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 29)
  - Development/Strategic Plan, 1996-1997 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 30)
  - Dobbs, Lou, 1997 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 31)
  - Duncan, Dick, 1998-1999 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 32)
  - E-Books Steering Committee, 2000 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 33)
  - Electronic Rights Policy, 1994 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 34)
  - Ellis, Rosemary, 1997 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 35)
  - Entertainment Weekly, 1997-1998 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 36)
  - Farrell, Greg, 1998 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 37)
  - Fedor, Melissa [RESTRICTED], 1999 (Offsite-box R38)
  - Financial Miscellaneous [RESTRICTED], 1996-1998 (Offsite-box R38)
  - Forman, Craig: Time Digital Weekend, 1996-1997 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 38)
  - Fortune: General, 1997 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 39)
  - Fortune: Gift Recording Sets, 1997 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 40)
  - Gabler, Neal, 1997 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 41)
  - General Ind. Info (Internet advertising), 1996 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 42)
  - Goldstein, Jared, 1997 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 43)
  - Goodgame, Dan (Personal TIME), 1998 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 44)
  - Goodman, Mark [RESTRICTED], 1996-1998 (Offsite-box R38)
  - Gubbins, Bill, 1996-1998 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 45)
  - Hershey, Terry, 1998 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 46)
  - Hewlett Packard [RESTRICTED], 1998 (Offsite-box R38)
  - Hot Dots (personal e-shopper), 2000 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 47)
  - InStyle, 1997 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 48)
  - Internet Content Coalition, 1997-1999 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 49)
  - Iseman, Peter, 1997 (Offsite-box 3829, Folder 50)
  - Katz, Don: Audible Inc., 1998 (Offsite-box 3830, Folder 1)
  - Kessler, Judy, 1996 (Offsite-box 3830, Folder 2)
  - Libassi, Paul, 1996 (Offsite-box 3830, Folder 3)
  - Life [empty], circa 1996 (Offsite-box 3830, Folder 4)
  - Madoff, Steven: The Women's Channel, 1998 (Offsite-box 3830, Folder 5)
  - Marshall, Jessica, 1997 (Offsite-box 3830, Folder 6)
  - McCutcheon, Linda, 1997-1998 (Offsite-box 3830, Folder 7)
  - McCutcheon, Linda: Point of View (Business Issues), 1996 (Offsite-box 3830, Folder 8)
  - McKean, Kevin: Money.com, 1998 (Offsite-box 3830, Folder 9)
  - McKinsey: 1998 Strategic Plan, 1997 (Offsite-box 3830, Folder 10)
  - Memoranda, 1997-1998 (Offsite-box 3830, Folder 11)
  - Money, 1997 (Offsite-box 3830, Folder 12)
  - Naythons [empty], circa 1996 (Offsite-box 3830, Folder 13)
  - NuvoMedia, Inc. [RESTRICTED], 1998 (Offsite-box R38)
  - Pathfinder Offsite Presentation, 1996 (Offsite-box 3830, Folder 14-15)
  - Pathfinder Policies and Standards, 1997-1998 (Offsite-box 3830, Folder 16)
  - People, 1998 (Offsite-box 3830, Folder 17-18)
  - Personnel, 1996-1997 (Offsite-box 3830, Folder 19)
  - Petrow, Steven, 1997-1998 (Offsite-box 3830, Folder 20)
  - Photography, 1996 (Offsite-box 3830, Folder 21)
  - Press, Gail, 1998 (Offsite-box 3830, Folder 22)
  - Rivera, Ed, 1997 (Offsite-box 3830, Folder 23)
  - Roadrunner/Marlowe Teig, 1996 (Offsite-box 3830, Folder 24-25)
  - Royte, Elizabeth [RESTRICTED], 1998 (Offsite-box R38)
  - Softbook Press, 1998-1999 (Offsite-box 3830, Folder 26-28)
  - Softbook Press [RESTRICTED], 1998 (Offsite-box R38)
  - Softbook Press II [RESTRICTED], 1999 (Offsite-box R38)
  - Softbook Press III [RESTRICTED], 1999 (Offsite-box R38)
  - Sports Illustrated, 1997 (Offsite-box 3830, Folder 29)
  - Sports Illustrated for Kids, 1997 (Offsite-box 3830, Folder 30)
  - Tenti, Gianluca, 1998 (Offsite-box 3830, Folder 31)
  - Territo, Joe: Editorial Management Group, 1997 (Offsite-box 3830, Folder 32)
  - Thrive, 1995-1997 (Offsite-box 3830, Folder 33)
  - Time, 1997 (Offsite-box 3830, Folder 34)
  - Time: Crime, 1997 (Offsite-box 3830, Folder 35)
  - Time for Kids, 1997 (Offsite-box 3830, Folder 36)
  - Time Global, 1997 (Offsite-box 3830, Folder 37-38)
  - Time: International Use of Domestic, 1997 (Offsite-box 3830, Folder 39)
  - Time in New Media Task Force, 1998-1999 (Offsite-box 3830, Folder 40)
  - Wired, 1998 (Offsite-box 3830, Folder 41)
  - Woods, Dan, 1997 (Offsite-box 3830, Folder 42)